Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
My Lady, this ointment was specifically
made for you by the Imperial Infirmary.
You have been losing weight, My Lady,
and this will help keep your skin firm.
Apply more on my waist.
I'm finished, My Lady.
Coua, help me…
My Lady, are you all right?
My Lady, My Lady!
Concubine An fainted
in the Palace of Prolonging Happiness.
Has an imperial doctor examined her yet?
An imperial doctor went to her palace,
but Concubine An did not admit him.
Concubine An's servant told the imperial doctor
that Concubine An fainted due to her
excessively restricted diet.
Why is she on a diet?
I heard that ever since Concubine An fell out of favor,
she has been secretly practicing ice dancing.
An Lingrong's idea to regain favor by becoming
an ice dancer shows thoughtfulness.
Every emperor of the Great Qing has shown
great appreciation for that art.
There is a performance on the ice every winter.
Ice dancing is also among the four national customs of the Great Qing,
along with the Manchu language,
wrestling, and horseback archery.
One of the prior emperor's personal guards
gained high status by ice dancing.
How does Your Highness plan to counter this?
We need not do anything at all.
She is "seeking the path to her own doom."
The path to her own doom?
I'm too dull-witted to understand, Your Highness.
One can only succeed in ice dancing
if they are trained since childhood.
It requires a slender figure, and flexibility -
as if the dancer had no bones.
It cannot be mastered overnight.
Although An Lingrong is delicate,
She is no longer slender
after so many years of luxury in the palace.
No wonder she restricted her diet.
It is as Your Highness says.
Dieting will affect her looks, but it takes a long time.
She must be burning with anxiety.
But there is a way she could get instant results.
If someone were to tell her,
I'm sure she would feel as if she found treasure.
Then we must not let her find out about this method.
On the contrary, we must let her find out.
Zhao Feiyan was the "flying swallow"
favored by Emperor Cheng of Han.
She was so delicate that
she could dance on a man's palm.
It was because she used the Flesh Thinning Pill.
Place the pill in your belly button,
and it melts into your body.
It will make your skin as fair as snow
and your body as light as a swallow.
Your face will shine with radiance.
But the pill contains musk as an ingredient.
Musk damages women's bodies.
It not only causes infertility but also
will cause miscarriage in a pregnant woman.
Concubine An is most knowledgeable about spices.
I fear the musk can't be concealed from her.
I know that we cannot conceal it,
and I don't want to hide it from her.
It's her choice whether or not to use the Flesh Thinning Pill.
I've heard that bathing with golden azalea petals
can counteract the yin toxins of musk.
Perhaps Concubine An also knows of this method.
If that really worked,
then how is it that Feiyan and her sister Hede
possessed supreme power but bore no children?
They were able to bathe with all the golden azalea under Heaven.
It's just as well she knows of this.
If she thinks golden azalea will help,
she will use the pills even more recklessly.
Did you give the Flesh Thinning Pills to Concubine An?
Yes. She took them without a word.
She is quite obedient.
She had already asked the Imperial Infirmary for the pills
before Your Majesty granted them to her.
It seems she really has given up on having children.
Isn't that wonderful? It saves us much effort.
That's right. A childless concubine makes a harmless pawn.
The pill is incredibly effective.
My Lady has indeed become much slimmer these days.
But the medicine is too powerful, and I'm worried that...
There's nothing to be worried about.
Tomorrow is New Year's Eve.
I know how much musk it contains.
I've drawn a bath with golden azalea petals for Your Highness.
I've already taken enough tonics of every kind these past years.
The bath won't make any difference.
My Lady, you haven't been able to bear a child for His Majesty.
You should think of a solution.
I'm controlled by others.
I can't even be the one to decide on my own pregnancy.
Do you know how much I hate all of this?
But Coua, I have no other options.
I have to obey the Empress.
Last year's ice dancing was even better.
Especially the rendition of
"Nezha Conquers the Dragon's Sea".
The founding emperor Nurhaci was a great ice skater.
His troops on ice could move even faster
than the cavalries on horses.
I heard that when Your Majesty was still Lord IV,
you won grand awards in the contest of
horseback archery on the ice every year.
"If the north wind can hear the plum flowers,
spare the blooming wishes for a peaceful spring."
Our story began with plum flowers.
Your Majesty still remembers.
"Her pleasant scent accompanied by poetic charm;
she is so freshly elegant that she cannot feel the winter cold."
"If the north wind can hear the plum flowers,
spare the blooming wishes for a peaceful spring."
Does Your Majesty remember that my sister
liked to recite this poem when you and she were first married?
I'm honored to know that Empress Première
also appreciated the purity of plum flowers.
You and Première are both of a pure nature.
Concubine An.
Grace to Your Majesty.
Has your voice still not recovered?
My voice was damaged by something I ate.
I'm afraid it will never fully recover.
You are not wearing enough clothes while still recovering,
and your hands are cold.
Su Peisheng, hand me my marten coat.
Don't get sick in this freezing weather.
It's a pity that your voice is damaged.
"You lose something at sunrise,
you gain something at sunset."
Although Concubine An's voice is damaged,
her dance on the ice just now could surpass Feiyan.
I think Concubine An deserves to be called "Feiyan on the ice".
It reminds me of Lumière's Dance of the Startled Swan.
She also looked like an immortal from Heaven.
Noble Consort Lumière's performance was stunning,
and yours was swift and elegant.
You both have your merits.
I'm blessed to have you both.
How dare I compare to Her Noble Highness?
I am just "the ugly Dong Shi imitating the beautiful Xi Shi".
I have not yet asked, why did you dare perform today?
I yearned for Your Majesty so much.
I just wanted to be able to look at Your Majesty;
even a glimpse from afar would have satisfied me.
I have not Heaven's blessings to be able to serve Your Majesty.
To dance for you today has been "an honor in three lives".
Since it was inappropriate for me to come out,
now that my dance is over,
I will accept any punishment that Your Majesty bestows.
All right, all right.
Stay with me for the New Year.
Consort Lumière has safely given birth to the heirs.
But Lingrong, before Concubine Vertu gives birth,
don’t go to the Palace of Pearl Jade.
I'm honored to obey Your Majesty.
Since Concubine Vertu and I are close like sisters,
I can't help but feel guilty
that I am unable to take care of her personally.
What a minx!
May my Emperor live and reign for ten thousand years,
and ten thousand of ten thousand years.
"Lotuses are harvested south of River Yangtze.
How endless their verdant canopy expands!"
His Majesty has been favoring Concubine An recently.
If this continues, it is only a matter of time before she becomes a Consort.
She hasn't had it easy.
Her appearance is not the best of the best.
Let alone her family background
and the fact that she has no children.
But she's been able to make it to today's status.
All she does is act pitiful to gain sympathy.
I can't believe His Majesty would fall for her tricks.
It is not just His Majesty.
Not a man under Heaven could refuse a woman like her.
My Lady, you've kept that bracelet in storage.
Why did you take it out today?
This was bestowed by His Majesty.
Such treasures are rare nowadays.
I want you to take it to the
Palace of Prolonging Happiness and present it to her.
The tributary jadeite is getting worse year by year.
And yet you are giving such nice jewelry to her.
I can only pity such excellent jade.
What pity are you speaking of?
Tell me, too.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
What lax servants outside!
They didn’t announce the arrival of Your Majesty.
I was afraid you were napping, so I didn't want to wake you up.
I didn’t realize you were having a private chat.
Rise.
I asked Jade to look for something.
Please take a look, Your Majesty. What do you think?
This seems to be what I rewarded you last time.
You cherish it so much that you can't even bear to wear it.
Why did you take it out?
I don't have the heart to wear it,
but I want to give it to Lingrong.
Even Jade said, "If such good jewelry isn’t worn by a beauty,"
"what a pity it is for the jadeite."
The Empress has also showered her with rewards.
The items provided by the
Household Department have been ample.
It’s nice that she has already received generous rewards.
but my sincerity is a different matter.
But in order to “present the Buddha with borrowed flowers”.
I still need to ask for Your Majesty’s permission.
I see you have been wearing a new coral bracelet.
It looks pretty.
Coral is not a precious material.
I know that An likes jadeite,
which is why I want to give her this bracelet.
But Your Majesty is eyeing my other things for Lingrong.
Lingrong is not from a glorious family and is timid by nature.
There are a lot of concubines who dislike her.
Only you have been like a sister to her all these years.
What a rarity it is.
Huan Huan, I am in a dilemma about something.
Huan Huan may not be able to resolve Si Lang's concerns.
But I'm happy to be your audience.
It's about your parents.
I'm afraid that they may not be able to visit you
in the palace any time soon.
Why?
The Gūwalgiya Clan joined forces with many officials to oppose it.
They criticized me for being unjust due to personal favor.
Your Majesty is not unaware
that the accusations against my family could be
suspected of being a fabrication.
Moreover, Your Majesty also needs to consider Hongyan's future.
He cannot be the grandson of a guilty official.
Can Your Majesty ...
consider reinvestigating my family's case?
Noble Lady Délice has not committed any grave mistakes in the palace.
Also, The Gūwalgiya Clan hasn't given us
an angle to reopen the investigation.
Reinvestigating past cases without any reason
will only threaten the stability of the imperial court.
Your Majesty, I can wait.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Follow us to get updates on the translation progress.
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Your Noble Highness.
It's still chilly. Why does Venerable Prince Shen wear so little?
You should put on some warm layers.
I thank Your Noble Highness for your concern.
Her Majesty also reminded me when I was
paying my respects at the Palace of Longevity.
I think being well-fed and well-clad weakens one's character.
Thus I have chosen to wear thin clothes.
Elder sister, I've been looking for you.
If you don't go back now, Hongyan will start crying.
I don't think we've met, My Lady. I wonder...
Must every decent-looking girl be married to His Majesty?
I'm not a concubine.
Why are you mentioning the word marriage?
A girl should know what she can speak of.
Venerable Prince Shen, please don't feel like an outsider.
This is my younger sister.
She has rarely come out.
It is no wonder Your Lordship does not recognize her.
My sister grew up in a remote area.
She's uneducated about palace etiquette.
I hope she did not incur Your Lordship's ridicule.
Now, greet Venerable Prince Shen!
It's no surprise that Your Lordship
mistook me for a concubine.
In this palace, everyone with a pretty face
receives His Majesty's favor.
That was probably the reason for Your Lordship's speculation.
Yurao, that's enough!
Miss, you are very proud and haughty.
You seem to view His Majesty's power and wealth as nothing.
Perhaps ...
only the prestige of my brother, Lord XVII,
could catch your eye.
Why?
Do worthy men exist only in the imperial family?
I'd rather live a coarse life with a commoner
than marry into any imperial palace or estate.
It was my discourtesy. I underestimated you.
My sister always talks bluntly but she didn't mean any offense.
I hope Your Lordship won't mind her.
Let's go, sister.
What's with you today?
What's on your mind?
You can't suppress your smile.
I'm not smiling.
Don't lie to me. You can't hide anything.
Come on, tell your 17th brother.
I met a girl with such a strong personality.
Also, she thinks we are not good enough for her.
True. What's good about us?
All we have is birth into the imperial family.
But, people have been stripped of their noble titles,
and brothers have died fighting each other for the throne.
That is nothing to be envious of.
Brother XVII, enough of these depressing words.
Let's race!
Let's go!
Your Highness, Dr. Wen is here for routine pulse-taking.
Send him in.
Peace to Your Highness.
Don't be bound by formalities.
How is Meizhuang's prenatal qi?
Concubine Vertu is going to deliver in less than half a month.
She's been cultivating a peaceful mind for the baby
these months and her prenatal qi is very stable.
Although every time you tell me the same thing,
your words bring peace to my mind each time.
So many old acquaintances are gone over the years,
but fortunately, I still have you and Meizhuang.
Yes. Luckily the most important people are still here.
And Mr. Zhen is much better now, Your Highness.
Please don't worry, I'll visit him whenever I can.
It's not convenient for me to leave the palace.
So I have to trouble you to take care of my father.
I'll go visit Mr. Zhen often
after Concubine Vertu gives birth to the baby safely.
Sister.
My Second Lady, you ran so fast!
Be more careful!
Jinxi will take care of us, you may leave now.
Yes.
Xiao-Yunzi is playing paper cranes with Hongyan.
Do you want to join them? It's fun.
You can go by yourself.
Peace to Your Noble Highness.
Mr. Su.
His Majesty asked Your Highness to visit the Sixth Prince
in the Imperial Nursery with him after lunch.
All right. Thank you for coming over and telling me, Mr. Su.
That's so kind of Your Highness.
Is Jade not here today?
That's fortunate. Otherwise, she'll be sad after hearing this.
As Your Highness knows,
Lord XVII has not been in good health since this spring
and has had several fevers.
The doctor said he has been invaded by cold qi.
Yesterday afternoon he rode horses with Venerable Prince Shen.
The horse lost its temper and His Lordship fell off.
His injuries aren't bad,
but at night his fever was burning up again.
I have to report this to Her Majesty the Empress Dowager
and make her aware of the situation.
Such a grave matter...
Why didn't anyone tell me?
Your Highness is busy with the palace affairs.
How can we bother Your Highness with such matters?
In addition, Her Majesty the Empress
always manages the affairs of the extended family.
Yes. I was just thinking about ...
Her Majesty's health.
She also has to look after the Empress Dowager.
So I inqured about it.
Your Highness shows kindness to the entire harem.
It's only natural for you to care for the lords.
Even if it doesn't concern Your Highness,
you'd still ask about it for Jade's sake.
Go report to the Empress Dowager now.
I take my leave, Your Highness.
Yurao, I'm feeling tired.
How about you go play with Hongyan and Lingxi?
Can I bother you ... with this?
I can't rest assured if anyone else goes and visits.
You still cannot move on from him?
It's because of me that he became so susceptible to the cold.
I owe him too much.
Can I ask you to help me repay my indebtedness?
You're worried about his health?
You should go visit him.
Do what I cannot do - for me.
At least, it would bring peace to one more person.
Really?
But how do I... get out of the Palace?
Go talk to Su Peisheng.
He'll grant you this wish.
Go.
My Lady, are there any messages
that you need me to deliver for you?
I have no messages.
You can go now.
Huan'er...
Your Lordship.
Ajin. His Lordship is awake. Bring some tea.
You're awake, Your Lordship.
Your Lordship.
Did Huan'er send you here?
No...
I begged Mr. Su to let me come.
Thank you for taking care of me these days.
You should go back and help Huan'er in the palace.
It inconveniences her to be left alone.
There's no hurry. Jinxi is in the palace with her.
Your Lordship is unwell.
If I don't take good care of Your Lordship,
nobody will be at peace.
And my effort to come here would be wasted.
If you wish.
How come His Majesty hasn't been visiting the harem recently?
There's a lot going on in the court.
And the Grand Council is being set up.
His Majesty is too busy.
No wonder.
The Empress seems to have more energy these days.
I heard Noble Lady Délice
invited a nun from outside to give a sermon.
Do the priests in the Baohua Hall not satisfy her?
I heard that
Lady Délice repeatedly claimed to be feeling unwell,
and said it annoyed her to always see the same priests
in the Baohua Hall.
At the worst, she can bring in a nun from the state temple.
I should have paid more attention to it.
I think this jianzi is already perfect.
But Her Majesty ordered me
early in the morning
to teach the new maids the rules in the palace.
I didn't have time to attend to it all day.
It's fine.
Oh, Su Peisheng told me today that
His Lordship's fever is gone.
But he still needs to rest in bed for a few days.
And he also said Jade
may need to stay a few more days.
Sometimes, I'm really envious of Jade.
Sister, are you jealous of her freedom to go out of the Palace?
The Palace of Eternal Longevity is grand,
but you can only see the sky in a small square.
It's not as free as being outside of the palace.
Yes, I'm jealous that she gets to go outside at times.
You know I prefer being out,
but right now I genuinely want to stay here to accompany you.
This is a new breed of balsam.
It's called “the drunken rouge."
It's very pretty to color your nails with it.
It's rare to be grown in early spring.
It looks so nice on your nails.
Peace to Your Noble Highness.
Rise.
Her Majesty the Empress requests your presence
immediately at the Palace of Great Benevolence.
What's the matter?
It's a serious matter. Please ask Her Majesty.
I'm not at liberty to say anything.
Prepare the sedan chair.
Your Lordship has just recovered.
Be careful not to catch a cold again.
Thank you.
Your Lordship must see yourself as an outsider
if you stand on such courtesies with me.
Look at the kite in the sky.
It's flying so high,
but it's only tied to a thin thread.
How unstable.
Does Your Lordship like to watch kites fly?
No, I'm just thinking of Huan'er.
In her current situation she is just like a kite.
Jade,
I'm fully recovered.
You can go back and help Huan'er.
Please don't worry, Your Lordship.
Her Highness has His Majesty and his children.
She fears nothing.
Noble Lady Délice, you insisted on reporting
against Noble Consort Lumiere.
And you asked me to invite the entire harem.
What is it about?
I'm reporting on Noble Consort Lumiere's adultery.
Death would be a merciful punishment for desecrating the harem!
Defamation is a serious offense in the palace.
Lady Délice, how dare you make baseless accusations!
If half a word I say today proves to be false,
let me get struck by the Five Thunders,
never to be reborn.
What kind of oath is that?
Nobody knows the timing of their life and death.
Swearing on something so intangible
only shows how insincere you are.
I swear on the whole Guwalgiya clan,
if I make any false accusation,
my clan will end with no heirs.
You accuse Noble Consort Lumiere of adultery,
then who's her adulterer?
Imperial Doctor Wen Shichu.
Wen Shichu is Noble Consort Lumiere's most trusted doctor.
He takes her pulse every day.
It's no surprise if they gradually developed affection towards each other.
Besides, I heard Noble Consort Lumiere was unwell
for a long time when she first entered the palace.
Back then, it was Dr. Wen who took charge of her treatment.
Attendant Kang does have a good memory.
That must have been when this sinful relationship started.
How could you two make such speculations?
It's only natural that Noble Consort Lumiere
was treated by Dr. Wen.
Not only is Dr. Wen highly skilled in medicine,
but he also had a good relationship with Lumière's maiden family.
Naturally, they are supposed to look after each other in the palace.
How could you accuse them of adultery for that?
If that's the case, they're bosom friends since childhood.
Then it looks like there is some sense
in what Noble Lady Délice is saying.
You all are jibber-jabbering gossip and nonsense.
Do you have any evidence?
Of course I have evidence, Your Highness.
Before Noble Consort Lumiere entered the Palace,
Wen Shichu even went to her family to propose marriage.
Bring Chen Si's wife here.
Noble Lady Délice, you sit down.
Yes.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Raise your head and speak.
Bin'er?
You're Bin'er.
Noble Consort Lumiere still remembers her.
Her husband Chen Si serves in my maiden family.
When the Zhen family was convicted,
all their servants were confiscated and sold off.
If my family didn't buy her and feed her,
she would've already starved to death on the street.
Bin'er, rise and say what you have to say.
I don't dare, Your Highness ...
Skip the chatter. Let me ask you,
when you were a servant of the Zhens,
did Wen Shichu propose marriage
to the eldest daughter of the Zhen family,
that is, Noble Consort Lumiere, here in front of you?
Speak aloud before Her Majesty!
Didn't Chen Si tell you the rules?
Half a month before the Concubine Selection,
Dr. Wen did visit and propose marriage.
But...
But it was not said in front of Mr. and Mrs. Zhen.
He proposed in private... to Noble Consort Lumiere.
Did Noble Consort Lumiere accept?
No, No! Noble Consort Lumiere...
Your Majesty, in my view,
if Noble Consort Lumiere had feelings for Dr. Wen,
she wouldn't be a concubine in the palace today.
We can see that Noble Consort Lumiere has nothing to hide
and has no private feelings for Dr. Wen.
Back then, Noble Consort might think
a mere doctor did not deserve her.
But if Noble Consort Lumiere showed no feelings at all,
why would Dr. Wen propose to her so abruptly?
It must be that they shared some affection since childhood.
Your Majesty, I do not believe in childhood affection.
I believe that Heaven determines one's destiny.
Even after "a thousand twists and turns in the mountains",
one will still be reunited with their fate.
This cannot be changed by man.
Noble Lady Délice, I have always known that
you hold a deep grudge against Noble Consort Lumiere.
But "one's mouth and tongue can give rise to chaos".
You must not speak baselessly.
If it's truly like what you said,
that Noble Consort Lumiere and Dr. Wen had private feelings,
they would hide it carefully, and not let others know.
"The crime no one knows of is the crime you've never committed."
"If you loosen your foot bindings frequently,
your horse-size feet will be seen."
The new maid Petunia from the
Palace of Eternal Longevity saw it several times.
Petunia, report what you saw,
what you heard, and when;
tell me everything with no detail omitted.
That day, Her Noble Highness and Dr. Wen were talking,
and not many servants were serving inside.
I went in accompanying Yurao, My Second Lady.
And I would never...
expect to see...
Dr. Wen's hand holding Her Highness's hand,
and they both were looking at each other,
sitting still.
When Dr. Wen saw My Second Lady and me,
he hastily withdrew his hand.
I also saw Dr. Wen's sleeve was rolled up slightly.
It was embroidered with a delicate pattern of five bamboo leaves.
Afterwards, the more I thought about it,
the more scared I felt.
I was afraid that if Her Highness found out,
she'd kill me so I could never speak of it.
So I begged Lady Délice to help me.
Even a new maid saw it.
I wonder how many times such a thing has happened
when no one was observing.
This is a serious concern.
Ask Dr. Wen to come to the Palace of Great Benevolence.
Yes.
My Lady, your due date is approaching.
The Empress Dowager said you should not be disturbed
by whatever happens outside.
Move. Noble Consort Lumiere is implicated.
I have to go see what's going on.
His Majesty will definitely be notified.
His Majesty will help the Noble Consort.
Please rest assured, for the baby.
If something really happens,
it won't be too late for you to go then.
The baby in your belly is more important than anything right now.
All right.
Astragalus, two maces;
Ejiao gelatin, three maces;
Codonopsis, five maces.
Mr. Jiang.
Dr. Wen, Her Majesty is asking you
to visit the Palace of Great Benevolence now.
I have never served Her Majesty.
Why is Her Majesty summoning me?
That's something you should ask yourself.
Dr. Wen, please.
Sir,
I haven't checked
Concubine Vertu's pulse today.
This was specifially ordered by the Empress Dowager.
It'd be a sinful offense if the task is delayed.
What do you intend to do then?
Please allow me to check her pulse,
and then I will go with you immediately.
Go ahead then.
Your Highness is due soon.
I added some herbs
in your prescription
to ensure that during labor,
everything will go smoothly and you'll experience less pain.
You seem to be in a hurry.
Are you going somewhere?
Some herbs are in shortage at the imperial infirmary.
I was assigned to take care of it.
It's windy. Don't go outside today
in case you catch a cold.
Yes. Please come back soon.
I... have important matters to discuss with you.
Your Majesty, Dr. Wen is here.
Peace to Your Majesty. Peace to My Ladies.
Rise.
I cannot avoid this offense, Dr. Wen.
This embroidered pattern is unique.
Has it always been there?
Your Majesty, my mother loves green bamboo,
and therefore she embroidered
the bamboo leaves at my sleeve openings
to remind me of my family.
Your Majesty,
I believe the embroidered pattern on Dr. Wen's sleeves
has always been there.
Anyone could have seen it at any point in time.
It doesn't prove anything.
That's strange.
When a humble doctor meets the Noble Consort,
how come he acts as if he was in his own residence,
rolling up his sleeves while talking to her face to face.
If this continues, in the future,
when the doctor visits the Noble Consort,
they'll both be rolling up their sleeves
and unbuttoning their shirts.
Is there anything they're forbidden to do?
That day, Noble Consort Lumiere summoned me
to report on Concubine Vertu's pregnancy.
When Her Noble Highness heard that everything was well,
she was pleased and awarded me tea.
I rolled up my sleeves while drinking tea,
and lost my manners.
It's all my fault, Your Majesty.
It is precisely because Noble Consort Lumiere
trusts no one else in the imperial infirmary
that she entrusted you to take care
of her good sister Concubine Vertu.
It looks like the relationship between
Noble Consort Lumiere and you is truly extraordinary.
My Lady, you...
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.